 result←years Projection3 drugs;MAT;temp
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Healthcare
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 1, Task 3
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   21] →    21
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [24  56] →    33
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [59  84] →    26
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [87 100] →    14
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →   100
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 2
⍝   For this problem I will explicitly change the ⎕ML variable since not all APLers use ⎕ML←2
⍝    as standard system variables
⍝
⍝ FOR MORE INFORMATION ABOUT THIS PROBLEM AND IT'S SOLUTION PLEASE VISIT
⍝    https://github.com/Aleph-GORY/Dyalog-APL-Challenge-2017


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝   Task 3 – Write a function named Projection3 to model the patient populations in each country
⍝
⍝   The study is extended to include other countries as shown in the table. Broadly speaking, the responsiveness of
⍝   patients to their respective drugs is the same for each country. You can assume that there are 1,000 to 3,000 new
⍝   occurrences each month, per country, also uniformly distributed.
⍝
⍝    T0 group patients
⍝               Drug A Drug B Drug C
⍝       England 70,000 30,000 20,000
⍝       France  65,000 32,000 12,000
⍝       Germany 40,000 19,000 10,000
⍝       Spain   93,000 31,000 26,000
⍝       Italy   55,000 35,000 18,000
⍝
⍝   Projection3 has the following syntax:
⍝    results ← years Projection3 drugs
⍝   The right argument is a 3-column matrix with one row per country and columns being:
⍝    [;1] – the number of patients currently taking drug A
⍝    [;2] – the number of patients currently taking drug B
⍝    [;3] – the number of patients currently taking drug C
⍝   The left argument is:
⍝    years – the number of years to run the projection
⍝   The result is a 7-column matrix with one row per country columns being:
⍝    [;1] – the number of surviving patients taking drug A
⍝    [;2] – the number of surviving patients taking drug B
⍝    [;3] – the number of surviving patients taking drug C
⍝    [;4] – the number of surviving patients in remission
⍝    [;5] – the number of deceased patients
⍝    [;6] – the number of patients who have dropped out
⍝    [;7] – the number of people who are not being treated
⍝


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ Now, it's time to chill out and see the fruit of our effort.
⍝ So far, we have managed to develop a mathematical formula that let us simulate a patient population
⍝ for one year or a century at almost the same speed. An O(1) computational complexity algorithm.
⍝
⍝ Since there is not much to say about the implementation of the solution, let me talk about the power of
⍝ the algorithm.
⍝ In this problem, we are working with other countries, and for each one, we are asked to model their patient population.
⍝ The question now is, What's the speed rate of countries per unit of time we can chek?
⍝ The nowdays average computers can do lots of operations per second, Whow many? you may wonder; well it depends on
⍝ plenty of factors (from its manufacture to its configuration), nevertheless four our demonstrative pruposes we can
⍝ assume that, in average, a computer can do 1E10 operations per second. Now, let's imagine that our algorithm needs
⍝ a 1000, no 10000, better yet, let's loose our minds and imagine our algoritm need A MILLION operations in order to model
⍝ a patient population. In that case, our computer would be able to model 10000 countries every second.
⍝ Now, they are abour 200 countries IN THE WORLD, in other words, we could model the patient population of ALL THE COUNTRIES
⍝ IN THE WORLD... 50 TIMES EVERY SECOND.
⍝ Even crazier, if we consider every country has 3000 states (lots of states by the way), and we would like to model the
⍝ patient population of ALL THE STATES IN THE WORLD, we would need JUST A MINUTE TO DO IT.
⍝ Pretty amazing right?
⍝ Being said that, let's implement the solution 
⍝
⍝ If you still had questions about the formulas (Bracketing, Order or Logic) deduced in the other tasks
⍝ or if you want to check the empirical modeling of this Task in a spreadsheet, remember to visit:
⍝   https://github.com/Aleph-GORY/Dyalog-APL-Challenge-2017
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

⍝ As we can see, this problem is solved by aplying the previous Task's Alogorithm to each of the rows in the matrix

 MAT←years Projection2¨⊂[2]drugs

⍝ Great, but we end up with a nested vector. Now we just need to build up the new Matrix
⍝ For this problem we will use the MIX function (Monadic ⊃[AXIS]). In order to do that we will assign ⎕ML←2
 temp←⎕ML           ⍝ We save the current ⎕ML value in a temporary variable
 ⎕ML←2
 result←⊃[2]MAT
 ⎕ML←temp           ⍝ Don't be rude and mess with other APLer´s WorkSpace

 →0