 (sa sb sc rem dec)←years Projection(a b c);x;y;z;deca;decb;decc
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Healthcare
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 1, Task 1
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1    21] →    21
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [24   48] →    25
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [51  160] →   110
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [163 181] →    19
⍝                         TOTAL LINES →   181
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables
⍝
⍝ FOR MORE INFORMATION ABOUT THIS PROBLEM AND IT'S SOLUTION PLEASE VISIT
⍝    https://github.com/Aleph-GORY/Dyalog-APL-Challenge-2017


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝   Task 1 – Write a function named Projection to model this patient population
⍝
⍝   In a group of disease sufferers, 120,000 people are being treated for a particular strain of the disease.
⍝     • On average, 2.5% of the total treated patient population will go into remission (that is, they will no longer
⍝       require treatment) each month after treatment.
⍝     • On average, a further 3.25% will die each year from the disease or due to complications resulting from it.
⍝
⍝     The treatment for this disease consists of three drugs A, B and C. Patients start on drug A and move through B and
⍝      on to C depending on their response (or lack of it).
⍝     At time zero (T0) the group has 70,000 patients taking drug A, 30,000 taking drug B and 20,000 taking drug C;
⍝      consider remission and death rates to be identical for all 3 drugs.
⍝ 
⍝   Projection has the following syntax:
⍝    (sa sb sc rem dec) ← years Projection a b c
⍝   The right argument consists of:
⍝    a, b, and c – the number of patients currently taking drugs A, B, and C respectively
⍝   The left argument consists of:
⍝    years – the number of years to run the projection
⍝   The result represents the population at the end of the projection and consists of:
⍝    sa, sb and sc – the number of surviving disease sufferers taking drugs A, B and C respectively
⍝    rem – the number of patients in remission
⍝    dec – the number of deceased patients 
⍝


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ As first approach, is obvious that the modeling of the Drugs can be solved in an iterative or even recursive way.
⍝ In principle, this idea seem pretty good (and tempting), all we would have to do is create a loop and transform
⍝ this problem into a simple implementation.
⍝
⍝ Nevertheless, APL was not designed for looping but for large calculations, and as we will see in Task 3, when we are working 
⍝ with large amounts of data, Iterative algorithms seems to never end. Why? Simple, almost all looping algorithms had upper bounds
⍝ in computational complexity of O(n) or O(n*2) meaning the bigger the input, the longer it takes to finish the computations.
⍝ What we want, then, is an algorithm that no matter the size of the inputs, it will always run in more less the same time, in
⍝ other words, we want an algorithm with complexity upper bound O(1).
⍝ We will achieve this throw mathematics, and dynamic optimization (DP), since is my bachelor's area and is more oriented to my thought process.
⍝ Is good to notice that a mathematical solution, A FORMULA in this case, represents more benefits to the problem than just a simple
⍝ "Run in time" propertie. Being generated the function, we will be able to extend this problem and the solution to the Calculus field,
⍝ where we can work with, derivatives, integrals, limits, that will let us know the instantaneous rate of change of the population, the limit
⍝ as we go closer to LONG periods of time, when does the population reach the maximus and minimous and a bunch of useful information
⍝ that the industrie and the guys in the lab just love.
⍝ I know it will be hard, but the benefits afford it.
⍝
⍝ First we must establish a temporal order in which the events happen, in order to avoid ambiguities and achieve a correct implementation.
⍝ We have two main events for every population:
⍝   -Every month a percentage of patients go into remission.
⍝   -Every year a percentage of patients dies DUE THE DISEASE OR COMPLICATIONS RESULTING FROM IT.
⍝
⍝ Now let's suppose without generality lost that every --half-- month, the remission diagnostics are executed and the percentage of patients
⍝ is removed from the population.
⍝ Similarly we will suppose the deaths occure at the end of the year since our simulation ends by that time.
⍝ The problem explicitly tells us that the patients dies DUE THE DISEASE OR COMPLICATIONS RESULTING FROM IT, this way, it's impossible
⍝ that a patient in remission dies DUE THE DISEASE OR COMPLICATIONS RESULTING FROM IT, with this in mind, we can say that only the sick
⍝ population will die every year.
⍝
⍝ Notice that the events, (going into remission) and (not going into remission) are mutually exclusive, and so their probabilities add up to 1.
⍝ Now, we can see that if a percentage of patients go to remission, the ones who are still taking drugs are the COMPLEMENT of the "Going to remission"
⍝ percentage. Let's call this complement x, logically the first percentage (the "Going to remission" one) will be (1-x).
⍝ Just as the events (going to remission) and (not going to remission), the events (die) and (not die) are mutually exclusive and their
⍝ probabilities add up to 1. Let's call the "Not die" percentage y, and it's complement "die" (1-y).
⍝
⍝ LET'S FOCUS ON THE REMAINING POPULATION
⍝ Knowing that the original population is P0, by the first month, there will be
⍝   P1 = P0x patients    ---→ The "not going into remission" percentage
⍝ By the second
⍝   P2 = P1x = P0x*2     ---→ Every month we multiply by x
⍝ Inductively we can ensure
⍝   P12 = P0x*12         ---→ By this time the last Remission diagnostic has been executed, so P12 is the sick population that will reach
⍝                               the end of the year
⍝ As we know, every end of the year a percentage (1-y) dies and a percentage (y) survives. So by the end of the year
⍝   P12y = POyx*12   patients survived    ---→ The "not die" percentage
⍝ By the end of the 1st month of the second year we will have
⍝   P13 = P12yx = P0yx*13   ---→ We multiply by x the current population
⍝ And by the 12th month of the second year
⍝   P24 = P12yx*12 = P0yx*24
⍝ End of the second year
⍝   (P12yx*12)y = P0(y*2)x*24=P0(yx*12)*2   ---→ you notice the pattern?
⍝ Inductively, the population by the end of n years will be
⍝   Pf=P0(yx*12)*n
⍝
⍝ Great, we had managed to came up with a final population formula, how can we deduce one for the deceased population?
⍝ LET'S FOCUS ON THE DECEASED POPULATION
⍝ Its clearly that by the end of a year, the remaining population is the population that NOT DIEd, and we could simply
⍝ obtain the population before die, doing the opposite thing we do in order to obtein the NOT DIEs population, that is by dividing by (y).
⍝ What we had now is the population by the end of the year but without any changes, in order to obtain the DIEd population
⍝ we just need to multiply by the DIE percentage.
⍝ We notice, then, that the DECEASED POPULATION is the sum of all the individual years deceased populations.
⍝
⍝ Let's write it down for better understanding
⍝   D1 = (1-y)(P0(yx*12)*1)÷y
⍝   D2 = D1 + (1-y)(P0(xy*12)*2)÷y ← (1-y)(P0(yx*12)*1)÷y + (1-y)(P0(xy*12)*2)
⍝ Generalizing
⍝   Dn = (1-y)(P0(xy*12)*n) + (1-y)(P0(xy*12)*(n-1)) + ... + (1-y)(P0(yx*12)*2)÷y + (1-y)(P0(xy*12)*1)
⍝ Pretty messy, right?, factorization is here to help us
⍝   Dn = P0(1-y)÷y((xy*12)*n + (xy*12)*(n-1) + ... + (xy*12)*2 +(xy*12)*1)
⍝ But, What on earth is that expression inside the parentheses?, it looks like we are going to make a loop for that right?
⍝ Well, fortunately (or maybe unfortunately) mathematics had a name for this kind of series, they are called GEOMETRIC SERIES
⍝ So what? So a lot, we can compute geometric series easily as follows
⍝ x*n+x*(n-1)+...+x*2+x+1=(x*(n+1)-1)÷(x-1)
⍝ Wait a second, there's no plus 1 in our parenthesis expression, this will never work.
⍝ Well not so fast, let's make one last factorization
⍝   Dn = P0(1-y)÷y(yx*12((xy*12)*(n-1) + (xy*12)*(n-2) + ... + (xy*12)*1 +1))
⍝ Applying the formula
⍝   Dn = P0(1-y)÷y(yx*12((yx*12)*n-1)÷yx*12-1)
⍝ Excellent we now have a deceased patients formula.
⍝ 
⍝ FINALLY LET'S FOCUS ON THE POPULATION IN REMISSION
⍝ Luckily for us if we managed to obtain the remaining and deceased population, there are no more patients that
⍝ those who are in remission, and since the death rate doesn't affect them, we calculate them as follows.
⍝ R = P0-Pf-Dn
⍝ 
⍝ Alright, now let's define the domain of our function, in other words, for which values of n ("years" in this case) our
⍝ function will work.
⍝ Do we want the domain to be continous, or discrete?, do we want to extend the function to the negative years or not? 
⍝ It's good to notice that Geometric series are defined as the sum of consecutive positive integer powers of a number.
⍝ Is no surprise then that in order to our function to work propertly, the values of n should be positive integers as well,
⍝ being said and since modeling the patient projection to, for example -2 years is iloggical, let's define the domain as n ≥ 0
⍝ where n is an integer.
⍝ What should the function do, then, if the user gives an n < 0?
⍝ In that case the function should return the default value n = 0.
⍝ And if the user gives a non integer n? 
⍝ In that case the function should return the projection to the closest greater integer.
⍝ And that's all we need to implement our answer.
⍝
⍝ As we can see, this solution just need to execute ONCE each formula and will not need of any looping or
⍝ nonoptimal method to show the answer. If you still had questions about the formulas (Bracketing, Order or Logic)
⍝ or if you want to check the empirical modeling in a spreadsheet, remember to visit:
⍝    https://github.com/Aleph-GORY/Dyalog-APL-Challenge-2017
⍝
⍝ AUTHOR THOUGHTS
⍝ Of all the problems, the Healthcare tasks were the more challenging, because of the terminology
⍝ and in some point ambiguity of the statements. I hope I had made myself clear with the explanations and
⍝ reasoning.
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---      

⍝ Domain Fix
 years ← ⌈0⌈years

⍝ Let's firt initialize the PROBLEM VARIABLES
 x←1-0.025 ⋄ y←1-0.0325 ⋄ z←y×x*12

⍝ With our formulary, this becomes a Straightfoward solution
 sa←a×z*years ⋄ sb←b×z*years ⋄ sc←c×z*years

 deca←(a×(1-y)÷y)×((z*(years+1))-z)÷(z-1)
 decb←(b×(1-y)÷y)×((z*years+1)-z)÷(z-1)
 decc←(c×(1-y)÷y)×((z*years+1)-z)÷(z-1)
 dec←deca+decb+decc

 rem←a+b+c-(sa+sb+sc+dec)

 →0