 r←k Cluster coords;CM;MV;C;SAME;T;i;COORD;D;CLUSTER
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Maths and Statistics
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 3, Task 3
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  42] →    22
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [45  93] →    49
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [96 131] →    36
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →   131
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ When defining clusters using the k-Means method, the first step is to find an initial partition. This is done by
⍝ selecting k points at random where k is the number of clusters you are trying to find. Next find the Euclidian
⍝ distance from each from the k initial points to every other point in the dataset and as first pass at defining clusters
⍝ on the data, group each point with the point from the initial partition that it is closest to (closest means has the
⍝ smallest Euclidean distance).
⍝
⍝ The data is now clustered but there is no guarantee that all the points are in the right cluster. Calculate the cluster
⍝ means and compare the Euclidean distance of each point with each of the cluster means. If it turns out that a
⍝ point is closer to another cluster mean than the cluster it was assigned in the first pass, reassign the point to the
⍝ cluster with the closer cluster mean. Let the iterative reallocation continue until no more reallocations occur
⍝ (although note that there are cases where there is no exact solution hence it is advisable to put a reasonable limit
⍝ on the number of iterations attempted).   
⍝
⍝   Task 3 – Write a function Cluster to compute cluster membership for a set of coordinates
⍝
⍝    Cluster has the following syntax:
⍝     r ← k Cluster coords
⍝    The right argument "coords" is a vector of coordinates in n-space.
⍝    The left argument "k" which is a single integer representing the number of clusters
⍝    The result is an integer vector where each element [n] represents the cluster number for coords[n]


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ This task is a bit of a tricky Implementation Problem, indeed we do not need to do any further reasoning
⍝ on the problem, but we do in the implementation. 
⍝  
⍝ We will do the next implementation:
⍝ 1.- First we will chose at random k points with the help of Dyadic ? (ROLL) since we should not pick the same
⍝   point twice
⍝ 2.- Here is where our iterations begin.
⍝   -The euclidean distance from any point is calculated (With dist formula) to the special points.
⍝   -Get membership with the closest point.  
⍝   This loop will keep going until no more rellocations (Membership changes) occur, or a fixed limit is reached
⍝
⍝ But, what's that fixed, limit?
⍝ As we can see in the code above, inside the big loop there are two other iterations.
⍝   The firt one, is executed on each coordenate the number of p⍝oints in the cluster mean
⍝       in other words, has a computational complexity O(k×⍴coords)  
⍝   The second one, is executed on each ⍳k, the function cMean, the number of points within a cluster
⍝       since cMean acts in every point of its argument, and knowing that every poins lies within a cluster
⍝       The second loop has a computational complexity of O((⍴coords)*2) 
⍝ Worst case scenario for loop one is when k tends to (⍴coords)÷2, adding both complexities, we end up with a
⍝ upper bound of O(n*2) with n←⍴coords
⍝
⍝ So What? So a lot, according to the upper bound, in the worst case scenario, we will be executing (⍴coords)*2 operations
⍝ per cycle. Now, we dont want to get an infinite loop, but we also dont want a mediocre clustering, and in top of
⍝ that, our time is gold. 
⍝
⍝ So, lets think of a huge data set, in wich there is no unique clustering and has a worst case scenario complexity
⍝ In informatics, the data sets we use are prety huge. lets suposse we are clustering the citizen's houses of a town
⍝ populattion in order to stablish in the cluster mean of each cluster, a brand new police station.    
⍝ Let's take for example León, Guanajuato in México (my Hometown). And supose there's a house for every 10 citizens.
⍝
⍝   Ciudad de México's population   ← 1 578 626     citizens
⍝   Ciudad de México's houses       ← 100 000 = 1E5 houses      ⍝ Let's aproximate a bit (Because of buildings and homeless)
⍝ 
⍝ The upper bound tells us that every iteration, the computer will do 1E10 operations. On average, a computer can make
⍝ around 1E10 operations every second, wich would mean our loop will be executed every second.
⍝ Great, now we know our algorithm works a loop per second with worst case scenario and a huge amount of data, now the
⍝ only thing we must ask ourselves is: how long do I want to wait, and even more important, how accurate I want to be.
⍝
⍝ The right thing to do, is to define a new function that takes (⍴coords) as an argument and returns the number of times
⍝ is wise to iterate in order to produce a good clustering in time.
⍝ Nevertheless, the expression "in time" is too ambiguous, in the las example, the government could take a week or even
⍝ a month in order to be sure where to place the police stations, but it could be a way diferent case.
⍝ For example, my "In time definition" is July 15th so InTime function keeps as a Problem to other APLer to solve  
⍝
⍝ So, finally, for this Clustering we will be using 60000 iterations, keeping in mind that the data will not exceed
⍝ by much the 1E4 elements in order to achive the clustering in 10 min (worst case scenario).
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

⍝ --Initial Partition
⍝ Lets select the k points at random and asign them to an array named CM (stands for Cluster Mean)
 CM←coords[k?⍴coords]

⍝ We initialize some variables for the looping
 MV←(⍴coords)⍴0  ⍝ A MembershipVector which will tell us to what nest is member an element
 C←0             ⍝ A counter which will place a fixed limit to the iteration
 SAME←0          ⍝ A boolean variable that will indicate if any rellocation ocurred

⍝ --Cicle
 :Repeat
    ⍝ We save the actual MembershipVector in a Temporary variable
     T←MV
    ⍝ The euclidean distance from each point to each Cluster Mean is calculated
     i←1
     :For COORD :In coords
         D←(⊂COORD)dist¨CM    ⍝ Computes the distance to each Cluster Mean
         MV[i]←D⍳⌊/D          ⍝ The Membership of the coordinate is changed to the closest nest
         i←i+1
     :EndFor 
    ⍝ The new Cluster Means are computed
     CM←⍬
     :For CLUSTER :In ⍳k
        ⍝ "(MV=CLUSTER)/coords" Returns an array with all the points within a cluster
         CM←CM,⊂cMean(MV=CLUSTER)/coords
     :EndFor
    ⍝ Variables Update     
     SAME←∧/MV=T     ⍝ Check if there had been any Membership Changes
     C←C+1           ⍝ Add one to the counter
 :Until (C>100)∨(SAME=1)  ⍝ If there hadn´t been any changes or we had pass the limit

 r←MV

 →0