  r←a dist b
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Maths and Statistics
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 3, Task 1
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  43] →    23
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [46  50] →     5
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [53  57] →     5
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →    57
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ Cluster analysis or clustering is the tasks of creating grouping within a dataset where each element in a group can
⍝ be said to be more similar to the other elements in its group than those of other groups. Clustering has many
⍝ useful applications in a variety of fields such as statistical data analysis, machine learning and pattern recognition,
⍝ just to mention a few.
⍝ 
⍝ There is a range of clustering methods. One popular methodology, centroid-based clustering, uses a central vector
⍝ to define each cluster. k-Mean clustering, another centroid-based clustering method, is a process whereby centers
⍝ for each cluster are established and the data objects are assigned to the nearest of the k cluster centres such that
⍝ the squared distances from the cluster centres are minimized.
⍝ First some definitions:
⍝
⍝  Euclidian Distance - The Euclidian Distance between two points A and B where A = (a1, a2,..., an) and
⍝   B = (b1, b2,..., bn) is: 
⍝       =(SUMATORY((ai-bi)*2))*0.5   
⍝
⍝   Task 1 – Write a function dist to compute the Euclidian distance between 2 points.
⍝
⍝    dist has the following syntax:
⍝     r ← a dist b
⍝    The left and right arguments are each single coodinates in n-space.
⍝    The result a scalar number representing the Euclidian distance between the coordinates.


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ This is a StrightFoward Solution Problem.
⍝ The vector oriented functions of APL will reduce all the calculation into a nice and elegant expression as folows
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

 r←(+/(a-b)*2)*0.5

 →0