 r←SigFig num;PV;N;DE;NZ;DP;SD
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Maths and Statistics
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 1, Task 1
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  41] →    21
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [44  80] →    37
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [83 142] →    60
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →   142
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ Significant figures of a number are digits that carry meaning contributing to its measurement resolution. For the
⍝ purposes of this problem, the rules for identifying significant figures are:
⍝   • All non-zero digits are significant.
⍝   • All zeros between the first and last significant digits are significant.
⍝   • If a number has neither decimal point, nor non-zero digits, then one zero, if any is present, is significant.
⍝   • All other leading zeros (those to the left of the leftmost significant digit) are not significant.
⍝   • In a number without a decimal point, trailing zeros (those to the right of the rightmost significant digit)
⍝     are not significant.
⍝   • In a number with a decimal point, trailing zeros (those to the right of the decimal point or rightmost
⍝     significant digit) are significant.
⍝
⍝ Task 1 – Write a function named SigFig that will determine the number of significant figures
⍝   SigFig has the following syntax:
⍝   r ← SigFig num
⍝   The right argument consists of:
⍝   num – a number, but may be given as a character scalar or vector, because APL will remove leading zeros
⍝   and trailing zeros to the right of a decimal point. For example, APL treats 100.00 as 100. You need not
⍝   consider them numbers using scientific notation (e.g. 1.234E56) or complex numbers (e.g. 1.2J3.4).
⍝   The result is the number of significant figures in num


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ As first step it’s clear that we must evaluate every rule we have into every digit of the number and then join the results into an boolean
⍝ array that will indicate whether or not the digit is significant.
⍝ In order to do that it's convenient to define a RULE HIERARCHY (determinate which ones are independents (evaluated first) and which ones
⍝ depends of other rules to be checked (or are easier to check) )
⍝
⍝ RULES
⍝	  1.- First one is independent and can be done in any moment.
⍝	  2.- Clearly to apply this rule is necessary to have ALL the other significant digits, in order to know First and Last.
⍝	  3.- The third rule also needs to wait till the end cause if the binary compression of RULES sum zero, it means that it has nothing but zeroes.
⍝	  4.- We need the leftmost significant digit in order to apply this rule.
⍝   5.- We must first determinate if the number has or not a decimal point.
⍝	  6.- Is independent and can be done in any moment.
⍝
⍝ Looks like we are going to code lots of rules right? Well... No. Indeed, after a little inspection it's clear that rule 2, 4 and 5 ARE THE SAME
⍝  they all ask us to make every digit between the first and last significant digit, a significant one. Meanwhile rule 3 is just a conditional.
⍝
⍝ And as we can see rule 1 and 6 are the only ones we need to evaluate. This binary array will contain all the information we’ll need.
⍝ Then we simply fill all the gaps between the first and last true element of the vector and apply the conditional.
⍝ Excelent, we now just need the deigits of the number in a separated and ordered way.
⍝
⍝ Wait, we had no problem with the character scalars or vector, because ever character is an independent element and a digit, done, but what about numbers?
⍝
⍝ We need a way to DECOMPOSE a numerical scalar into each of its DIGITS, and save them into a vector.
⍝ Decimal expantion will do perfect. The decimal expantion is an algorithm used a lot in maths and computer sciences for transforming a number into the
⍝ sum of its powers of ten. EXAMPLE→ 123=100+20+3=100 10 1 × 1 2 3.
⍝ Sadly, there´s no way to know how many digits a number has just by looking at it, what we DO can know is the maximum power of ten, the number is being
⍝ powered, How? with our friend the logarithm. But there's another problem still, logs dont tell us the number of digits after the decimal point
⍝ so in order to make a correct implementation we are going to do the decimal expantion until a fix limit.
⍝ Sounds arbitrary right? Well not so much, actually APL does it all the time, all APL calculations are perfomed to less than 20 significant digits.
⍝ So thats IT, our algorithm will make decimal expantion from the gratest power of ten the number reach till the 40th lesser power (Yes we doubled the number)
⍝
⍝ Its good to remember that when we type a numerical scalar such as 005, Apl will just see a 5, and 45.0100000 as 45.01, because of that, when working
⍝ with numberical scalars there will be no need of aplying rule 4 and 6, so we will just need to compute rule 1 and fill the gaps between the last number
⍝ and the first element of the vector, since it will always be a non zero digit or a significant zero
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

⍝ First, we check if we are working with a Number or
    ⍝ a Character Vector.
 :If (0=1↑0⍴num)
     →SF_NUM
 :Else
     →SF_CHAR
 :EndIf

⍝ --Subrutine for numbers
SF_NUM:
⍝ Let's initializate the power vector for the decimal expantion
 PV←1-⍳20
⍝ Then we need to know the power of 10 (N) the number is being powered
    ⍝ its good to remember that any power <-1 is a decimal point with some ceros
    ⍝ behind, which are SIGNIFICANT. Also, we can not take log of any number
    ⍝ ≤0, because of that we will conditionate the code with the cero, and take the absolute
    ⍝ value of the remaining numbers, without considering the MINUS SIGN as a Significant
    ⍝ Figure
 :If (num=0)
     r←1
     →0
 :EndIf
 N←¯1⌈⌊10⍟|num
⍝ Now we modify the power vector to the size of the number and convert it to its power of ten form
 PV←N+PV
 PV←10*PV
⍝ This function does the decimal expantion of the number
 DE←10|⌊num÷PV
⍝ Finaly we aply the algorithm discused above (Fill the gaps between the rightmost significant digit and the first element of the vector)
 r←+/∨\0≠⊖DE

 →0

⍝ --Subrutine for Character Vectors
SF_CHAR:
⍝ As I said above, first we need to get the first and last Significant Figure of the
    ⍝ array, who are dictated by the 1st and 6th Rules
 num←(num≠'-')/num  ⍝ We delete the MINUS SIGN if there is one
 NZ←num≠'0'         ⍝ Lets call NZ to the boolean vector who indicates all the NonZero digits.
 DP←∨\num='.'       ⍝ Lets call DP to the vector who indicates all the digits after the decimal point.
 SD←NZ∨DP           ⍝ SD is the mixture of both arrays.

⍝ Now we had stored in SD the first and last significant digit of num, we just had to
    ⍝ count all the digits in between them.
 SD←+/(∨\SD)∧⊖∨\⊖SD
⍝ There's only one detail, APL look at the decimal point in the character array as an
    ⍝ element of itself, (a digit for us), so if the number has decimal point we need to
    ⍝ substract one from the final result.
 :If (0≠+/DP)
     SD←SD-1
 :EndIf
⍝ Finally we check if it's a zero (AKA SD=0)
 :If ((SD=0)∧(0≠⍴num))  ⍝ It could be the empty vector
     SD←1
 :EndIf
 r←SD

 →0