 r←cMean coords
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Maths and Statistics
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 3, Task 2
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  42] →    22
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [45  49] →     5
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [52  58] →     7
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →    58
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ Cluster analysis or clustering is the tasks of creating grouping within a dataset where each element in a group can
⍝ be said to be more similar to the other elements in its group than those of other groups. Clustering has many
⍝ useful applications in a variety of fields such as statistical data analysis, machine learning and pattern recognition,
⍝ just to mention a few.
⍝
⍝ There is a range of clustering methods. One popular methodology, centroid-based clustering, uses a central vector
⍝ to define each cluster. k-Mean clustering, another centroid-based clustering method, is a process whereby centers
⍝ for each cluster are established and the data objects are assigned to the nearest of the k cluster centres such that
⍝ the squared distances from the cluster centres are minimized.
⍝ First some definitions:
⍝
⍝   Cluster Mean - The cluster mean is the average of the points in the cluster. For example, if you have the cluster:
⍝    {(1,1) (2,2) (3,2)} then the cluster mean is the point (2,1.66)
⍝
⍝   Task 2 – Write a function cMean to compute the cluster mean of a set of coordinates.
⍝
⍝    cMean has the following syntax:
⍝     r ← cMean coords
⍝    The right argument is a vector of coordinates in n-space
⍝    The result is a single n-space coordinate representing the cluster mean


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ This is a StrightFoward Solution Problem.
⍝ As in the last task the vector oriented functions of APL will reduce all the calculation into a nice and elegant expression.
⍝


⍝   --ALGORITHM--

⍝ The monadic disclosure is used because after the reduce function (/) the n element vector is reduced into a
 ⍝ nested scalar that must be hatched
 r←⊃(+/coords)÷⍴coords

 →0