 r←IQR vec;Q3;Q1
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Maths and Statistics
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 2, Task 1
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  47] →    27
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [50  58] →     9
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [61  74] →    14
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →    74
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ An outlier is an observation that lies an abnormal distance from other values in a random sample from a population.
⍝
⍝ There are many ways to define “abnormal distance” but for this problem we will be using the interquartile range
⍝ (IQR) to measure whether or not a point in a dataset is an outlier. There are two common ways to compute
⍝ quartiles when the data set has an odd number of elements, inclusive and exclusive, which dictate whether the
⍝ middle value of the data set is included or excluded when determining the medians of the lower and upper
⍝ portions of the data set. For the purposes of this problem, we will use the exclusive method:
⍝   1. Sort the data set.
⍝   2. Use the median to divide the ordered data set into two halves.
⍝       • If there are an odd number of elements in the original ordered data set, do not include the
⍝        median (the central value in the ordered list) in either half.
⍝       • If there are an even number of elements in the original ordered data set, split this data set exactly
⍝        in half.
⍝   3. The lower quartile value is the median of the lower half of the data. The upper quartile value is the
⍝   median of the upper half of the data.
⍝
⍝ The interquartile range (IQR) is the difference between the upper and lower quartiles.
⍝
⍝   Task 1 – Write a function IQR which finds the interquartile range of a vector of numbers
⍝
⍝    IQR has the following syntax:
⍝     r ← IQR vec
⍝    The right argument consists of vec - a numeric vector of at least 2 elements.
⍝    The result is a single number representing the vector's interquartile range
⍝


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ This is what is called a "StraightFoward Solution" or "Implementation" Problem.
⍝ All the steps and reasoning are described in the Problem Description and you just had to -as the names say-
⍝ go StraightFoward to the solution or do the Implementation.
⍝
⍝ For the sorting process I'll be using the monadic function ⍋ (Grade Up) although its posible to create
⍝ a personal sorting subrutine, such as bubble sort or quicksort.
⍝
   

⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

⍝ First, we sort the array in a non descendant order
 vec←vec[⍋vec]
⍝ Then, we separate the data in two halves, in order to compute the lower and upper quartiles
 Q1←(⌊(⍴vec)÷2)↑vec
 Q3←(-⌊(⍴vec)÷2)↑vec
⍝ The medians are computed
 Q1←(Q1[⌈(⍴Q1)÷2]+Q1[⌈(1+⍴Q1)÷2])÷2
 Q3←(Q3[⌈(⍴Q3)÷2]+Q3[⌈(1+⍴Q3)÷2])÷2
⍝ Finally, the diference is calculated
 r←Q3-Q1

 →0