 r←s SRound num;PV;N;DE
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Maths and Statistics
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 1, Task 2
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  34] →    14
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [37  66] →    30
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [69  97] →    29
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →    97
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1                     
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ Task 2 – Write a function named SRound which returns the next higher s-round number
⍝  Now let's call a number s-round if it has s or fewer significant digits.
⍝  A number that is s-round is also (s+n)-round for n>0.
⍝  For example, 12000, 1.2, and 100 are 2-round; 100 is also 1-round.
⍝
⍝ SRound has the following syntax:
⍝   r ← s SRound num
⍝  The right argument consists of:
⍝   s - a single positive integer which represents the maximum number of significant digits.
⍝  The left argument consists of:
⍝   num - a single number
⍝  The result is the first s-round number greater than or equal to num


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ From the past Task function (Problem 1 Task1), we deduced that the size (si) of the boolean vector with the significant digits of a number
⍝ is obtained by the FIRST and LAST significant digit.  
⍝ This is vital information, because in order to know whether or not a number num is an s-round number we must knog its significance.
⍝ Clearly, we are looking to implement a way to REDUCE the significance of a number, Why? because if the original number is not an S-R number,
⍝ means that it has BIGGER significance and needs to be REDUCED.    
⍝
⍝ Now let's make some observations. It’s clear that modifying the array in between is a waste of time, because as we said, the significance is related to
⍝ the FIRST and LAST significant digits, so the important thing is to modify those digits. But wich one? Its good to noticde that if we change the leftmost
⍝ digit, the effects on the number will be greater than the rightmost digit BY AT LEAST 1 POIWER OF TEN, with this in mind and knowing we want the FIRST
⍝ number greater than or equal to num we will be working with the rightmost number.
⍝ Observation 2: Since the input is a numerical scalar, the rightmost significant digit will be a non-zero digit
⍝ Right, but what do we do next? In order to reduce the number, we must transform the rightmost significant digit into a non-significant digit.
⍝  For this we must transform the rightmost significant digit INTO A 0. Because the trailing zeros does not matter, only after a decimal point,
⍝  but, since we are working with numerical scalars the trailing zeros after decimal point will never be displayed. 
⍝ Then, we simply add 1 to the current rightmost digit in order to obtain a greater number, since that dictates the problem.
⍝ 
⍝ We just had defined a method to transform a number (num) with significance (si) into a number with significance (si-1), notice that now we can extend the
⍝ algorithm to transform it into a number with significance s-n.
⍝ So in order to do this, we just need to transform the n rightmost significant digits into 0 and add 1 to the (si-n) digit.
⍝ Excelent, we just need to define whan n to use. Notice that the larger the n, the bigger the number gets, so we are looking to the smallest n for wich
⍝ (si-n) is an s-round number, so in order to achive this (si-n=s) because if n were smaller (si-n>s) wich is a contradiction to the definition, and if
⍝ n were bigger, the resulting number will be bigger, and we are looking to the FIRST greater number. 
⍝ 
⍝ Being so, we can redifine our algorithm as folows, since s=si-n.
⍝ In order to obtain the FIRST greater s-round number, we must add 1 to the s-th significant digit of the number and transform all the digits to the right
⍝ into 0s
⍝
⍝ Finaly, the decimal expantion will help us to achive this as folows. 


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

⍝ First, we check if the number which we are working on is already an s-round one
 :If (s≥SigFig num)
     r←num
     →0
 :EndIf

⍝ If not we proceed to execute the algorithm

⍝ As in the last task, let us first initializate the power vector for the decimal expantion
 PV←1-⍳20
⍝ Then we need to know the power of 10 (N) the number is being powered
    ⍝ this time we will not need to check for 0, because the minimun value of s=1, and
    ⍝ 0 is a 1-round number (the minimum value of s), so it will never get throw here
 N←¯1⌈⌊10⍟|num
⍝ Modify the power vector just like in task 1
 PV←N+PV
 PV←10*PV
⍝ Decimal expantion
 DE←10|⌊num÷PV
⍝ Now we add to the value in the s position
 DE[s]←DE[s]+1
⍝ We do the inverse process of the decimal expantion
 DE←DE×PV
⍝ Finally we sum the first s terms of the array, since the others does not matter
 r←+/s⍴DE

 →0