 r←point isInside nodes
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Computational Geometry
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: Problem 1, Task 2
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  37] →    17
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [40  53] →    14
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [56 134] →    79
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →   134
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ In or Out?
⍝ It's possible to determine whether a point is within the boundaries of a polygon by extending a horizontal line
⍝ from the point to another point beyond the boundaries of the polygon and then counting the number of
⍝ intersections with the polygon's edges. If the number of intersections is odd, the point lies within the polygon and
⍝ if the number of intersections is even, the point does not lie within the polygon.
⍝
⍝   Task 2 - Write a function isInside to determine if a point lies within a polygon.
⍝
⍝   isInside has the following syntax:
⍝    r ← point isInside nodes
⍝   The right argument nodes is a vector of node coordinates for the polygon drawn in either a clockwise or
⍝   counterclockwise manner.
⍝   The left argument point is a 2-element vector of the (x,y) coordinates for the point to be tested.
⍝   The result r is a Boolean scalar where 1 indicates the point lies within the polygon, and 0 that it does not.
⍝


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ All we need to know is in the problem description, all we have to do is extend the horizontal line outside the
⍝ polygon and count the Interections. So we just need to know the x coordinate of the rightmost point and extend
⍝ an horizontal line to that x coordinateplus 1 (for not having any type of error).
⍝ 
⍝ As we are going to be using our Intersects function, Is good to remember that if a segment intersects an edge, 
⍝ it will count two intersections, intead of one.
⍝ This is a HUGE PROBLEM, so in order to fix this, we will check first in 4 directions and evaluate with the point
⍝ who has no edge intersection.
⍝ Anyways, if all of the lines intersects edges, then we should extend 4 lines toward al posible combinations of
⍝ the leftmost and rightmost x coordinate with the downmost and uppermost y coordinate.
⍝ If all else fails, we should take the nomber of lines intersected by any line and substract 1.
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---



⍝ First we define the 4 farest directional points in the polygon
 max←⊃⌈/nodes           ⍝ We obtain the farest distance in +x an +y the polygon reach
 min←⊃⌊/nodes           ⍝ We obtain the farest distance in -x an -y the polygon reach
 points←⍬          ⍝ Empty list
 points←points,⊂(max[1]+1),point[2]    ⍝ To the East
 points←points,⊂point[1],(max[2]+1)    ⍝ To the North
 points←points,⊂(min[1]-1),point[2]    ⍝ To the West
 points←points,⊂point[1],(min[2]-1)    ⍝ To the South

 ⍝ Now we must compare this new segments with every side of the plygon
 n←0   ⍝ A counter which indicates the number of sides intersected
 N←⍬   ⍝ The vector where every n will be stored
 e←0    ⍝ A variable wich indicates the number of edges intersected
 E←⍬   ⍝ The vector wich tells us wheter or not an edge is intersected
 :For j :In ⍳4
    ⍝Default values
     n←0 ⋄ e←0
    ⍝ number of sides intersected
     :For i :In ⍳(⍴nodes)-1
         n←n+(points[j],⊂point)Intersects(nodes[i],nodes[i+1])
     :EndFor
    ⍝ number of edges intersected
     :For i :In ⍳(⍴nodes)
         e←e+(points[j],⊂point)Intersects(nodes[i],nodes[i])
     :EndFor

    ⍝ Assignation
     N←N,n
     E←E,×e
 :EndFor

 :If (0=×/E)     ⍝ If there was a line which didn't intersect an edge
     r←2|N[E⍳0]  ⍝ Check if the number of intersections onf that line is odd
     →0
 :EndIf

 ⍝ If all lines intersected an EDGE 
 
 ⍝ New points 
 points←⍬          ⍝ Empty list
 points←points,⊂(max[1]+1),(max[2]+1)    ⍝ To the Right upper corner
 points←points,⊂(max[1]+1),(min[2]-1)    ⍝ To the Right lower corner
 points←points,⊂(min[1]-1),(max[2]+1)    ⍝ To the Left upper corner
 points←points,⊂(min[1]-1),(min[2]-1)    ⍝ To the Left lower corner 
 
 n←0   ⍝ A counter which indicates the number of sides intersected
 N←⍬   ⍝ The vector where every n will be stored
 e←0    ⍝ A variable wich indicates the number of edges intersected
 E←⍬   ⍝ The vector wich tells us wheter or not an edge is intersected
 :For j :In ⍳4
    ⍝Default values
     n←0 ⋄ e←0
    ⍝ number of sides intersected
     :For i :In ⍳(⍴nodes)-1
         n←n+(points[j],⊂point)Intersects(nodes[i],nodes[i+1])
     :EndFor
    ⍝ number of edges intersected
     :For i :In ⍳(⍴nodes)
         e←e+(points[j],⊂point)Intersects(nodes[i],nodes[i])
     :EndFor

    ⍝ Assignation
     N←N,n
     E←E,×e
 :EndFor 
 
  :If (0=×/E)     ⍝ Lat time we check
     r←2|N[E⍳0]  
     →0
 :EndIf 
 
⍝ If all we find were edges then, pick one number of intersections, substract one and check 
 r←2|n-1

 →0