 r←Orientation(a b c)
⍝  ---INFO---
⍝
⍝ DYALOG APL COMPETITION 2017
⍝ -PROBLEM SET: Computational Geomatry
⍝ -PROBLEM AND TASK: -, -
⍝ AUTHOR: Armando Benjamín Cruz Hinojosa AKA Gory
⍝
⍝ INDEX                                 N.LINES
⍝
⍝ INFO:                     [1   18] →    18
⍝ PROBLEM DESCRIPTION:      [21  25] →     5
⍝ SOLUTION:                 [28  41] →    14
⍝ ALGORITHM:                [44  50] →     7
⍝                        TOTAL LINES →    95
⍝ SYSTEM VARIABLES
⍝ ⎕IO← 1 ⋄ ⎕ML← 1
⍝   I will not explicitly change this variables since they are almost always
⍝    every APLer standard system variables


⍝  ---PROBLEM DESCRIPTION---
⍝
⍝ One technique to determine if two line segments intersect is to use orientation. For more information on the use
⍝ of orientation, see http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/check-if-two-given-line-segments-intersect/.
⍝


⍝  ---SOLUTION---
⍝
⍝ For this problem I implemented the algorithm described in
⍝ http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/orientation-3-ordered-points/
⍝
⍝ We call orientation of points, to the path they form when we travel from one to another, it could be clockwise,
⍝ counterclockwise or colinear.
⍝ The way we are going to determinate this is throw point slopes.
⍝   -If  the slope from the first point to the second is lower than the slope from the second to the third,
⍝    the orientation is counterclockwise (left turn)
⍝   -Instead, if the slope from the first point to the second is greater than the slope from the second to the third,
⍝    the orientation is clockwise (right turn) 
⍝   -And if both slopes are equal, we say they are colinear.
⍝


⍝  ---ALGORITHM---

⍝ Let's firt initialize the PROBLEM VARIABLES

 r←×((b[2]-a[2])×(c[1]-b[1]))-(c[2]-b[2])×b[1]-a[1]

 →0